<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Crums of comfort for the mournful babe of hope from one that condoleth the distresse of the daughter of Sion ...</title>
            <author>R. B.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1664</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 60 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27228</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B165</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R27201</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09692179</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09692179</idno>
            <idno type="VID">44017</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A27228)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 44017)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1348:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Crums of comfort for the mournful babe of hope from one that condoleth the distresse of the daughter of Sion ...</title>
                  <author>R. B.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1664]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed: R.B.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Regeneration (Theology)</term>
               <term>Apostasy.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:44017:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Crums of Comfort for the Mournful Babe of hope; from one that condoleth the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe of the Daughter of <hi>Sion,</hi> that had been healed deceitfully, which cauſed her wound again to break out, for which ſhe hath ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red reproach; but the root of the matter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing throughly ſearcht into, ſhe is now come and invited to the day of a perfect Cure.</head>
            <head type="sub">Wherein the ground of all apoſtaſie and back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſliding from the Spirit of Truth, is diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and Objections anſwered, concerning the one Offering, that for ever hath perfected them that are ſanctified; how it can be but one Offering, or offered once for all, and yet he crucified afreſh; who in that he dyed once, dyeth no more, death hath no more domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and alſo how and when the apoſtaſie came in firſt?</head>
            <p>OH that my voyce might be hearkned unto! that it might rend the Clouds, and that my tender compaſſions might reach the higheſt thought of him that hath been exalted in the Seat and Throne of dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity <hi>[in the Heavens],</hi> and there hath been found accuſing the juſt, provoking God againſt the Inhabitant of the Earth; unto whom the woe is come, in what hath over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken him in the way of his ſojourning and travelling <hi>[on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward]</hi> toward the Land of Reſt, and City of everlaſting content; and thou poor diſtreſſed Babe of hope <hi>(in a better life and ſtate, than this world could afford thee)</hi> that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:44017:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
art ready at all times to cry out, <hi>What ſorrow is like unto my ſorrow? and what affliction like unto my grief?</hi> This being a day wherein the Sons of God hath come and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared before him, and Satan alſo hath come with them; that God could no ſooner ſay, <hi>Haſt thou conſidered theſe? and how they have walked before me with a perfect heart?</hi> [mark that;] but the Devil (that goeth about like a roar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Lyon, ſeeking whom he may devour, that ſaith, <hi>I come from walking up and down in the earth, and compaſſing about the ſame</hi>) is ready to reply, <hi>Doth theſe ſerve God for nought? haſt thou not done thus and thus for them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What ſhall I ſay unto thee, and for thee? thou art di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed and toſſed up and down, but not forſaken, and thou doſt not ſorrow as one without hope; for thou haſt yet a little ſtrength remaining; and ſure thy afflictions are come up before the Lord; but what am I, that I ſhould comfort thee? Only this is my hearts deſire, that my ſorrowful complaints might find a place for its yearn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to reſt, and that I might condole thy grief <hi>(in a fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-feeling of the ſame;)</hi> yea, and that the moan of my pierced, grieved, wounded ſoul <hi>(that I am ſure hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred the highest Heavens, and is come up before the Lord of Sabbaths;)</hi> might congratulate thy ſence <hi>[with me,]</hi> as a rebounding Eccho, and by the rebellious <hi>[in heart,]</hi> and ſtiff-necked <hi>[in ear,]</hi> might no more be ſlighted and diſ-regarded (as ſuch that cannot hear the voyce of the Charmer, though he charm never ſo wiſely:) but like the deaf Adder, are cloſed and ſhut up <hi>(againſt the breathings of the poor and needy, that dare not deſpiſe the day of ſmall things, but hath been thankfull for a crum:)</hi> And then their Heavens ſhall be no more like Braſſe, nor their Earth as Iron, nor ſhall an Iron finew be found on the neck <hi>(the place ſhe is to put on the harneſſe;)</hi> but the Heavens will hear the Earth, and the Earth will hear the Corn, and the Wine, and the Oyle, and they will hear <hi>Jezerel:</hi> that my words may drop toward the four winds of the Firmaments glory, where ſtars remain fixed to conſtel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late
<pb facs="tcp:44017:2"/>
matter of praiſe to him, that di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of what is luſtrous; where I ſeek entertainment <hi>[only]</hi> in the meek and lowly heart, whereby the worker of glory is <hi>endleſſe</hi>) hath his due and right in me, and all that wait on the power, that keeps and preſerves fixed, and from wandring out of, and above the place and ſphere we are ſerviceable <hi>[in]</hi> to the glory of the body, ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver dye, nor wax old;) Therefore</p>
            <p>Conſider with me <hi>[thou unpityed Babe]</hi> though thou art ready to ſay, None in all the earth like me; for I ſee the wicked flouriſh on every hand, and all things goeth well and are proſperous <hi>[with them;]</hi> but I am utterly unſtript of all earthly glorying and rejoycing <hi>(in any fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſelfiſh confidence;)</hi> and though I flye from the enemy, as one beſet with the terrours of the <hi>night;</hi> yet how doth he follow and ſurround me? and layes ſnares for my ſeer, and a Ginne and Trap to catch me <hi>in my way;</hi> ſo that my beſetments are even more than I am able to bear; and my roarings are all the day long, as one crying out of the belly of Hell, and out of the grave of ſorrow my moan aſcends, as he that the great Leviathan hath made to be his prey, and the Net of every Fowler hath been ſpread in my way, and the cunning Hunter hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued me <hi>[with Dogs;]</hi> that as a Partridge on <hi>the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of Iſrael,</hi> I have been hunted for my life, and had no place of ſafety, untill I came into the low valleys; though my ſoul panted after the Lord, more than the Hart for the water brooks: Alaſs for thee! I know thy day, and the night of thy ſorrow hath not been hid from mine eyes, but as one touched with the feeling of thy infirmity, I can condole with thee, being ſatisfied that thou canſt never ſit down and make an agreement with Hell and the Grave; nor is it poſſible <hi>[in this feeling]</hi> any contract ſhould be made with the wicked, to ſtrengthen the power and dominion of death, or inlarge the mouth of Tophet, and borders of deſtruction; yea, and though opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of returning back to thy wooted courſe, <hi>(in which
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:44017:3"/>
was a ſeeming pleaſure and content)</hi> are dayly preſented before thee, and inſtruments are ſuffered to be ſtirred up to that purpoſe, yet the very thoughts thereof, are a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance to thy ſoul; neither dareſt thou look back on the pleaſures of <hi>Egypt,</hi> as one longing for the Onions and Garlick <hi>[thereof,]</hi> and its Fleſh-pots (as did, and doth thoſe that were, and are found murmuring and repining, and complaining <hi>[by the way,]</hi> at the leadings of the Prophet, (whoſe carkaſſes fell in the Wilderneſſe,) that ſaid, <hi>Were there not Graves enough there?</hi>) Neither art thou again to be inchanted with the gluttony of <hi>Sodom,</hi> that looking back thou ſhouldeſt loſe thy ſhape.</p>
            <p>Oh dear heart! Look not out, for there is the Fools eye wandring abroad, neither look back, leaſt thou be an example <hi>[to ſavour and tincture the remaining part,]</hi> for concerning all ſuch that draw back, Gods Soul hath no pleaſure <hi>[in them,]</hi> becauſe their love grows cold, and ſuch are not fit for the Kingdome of God <hi>(that once had ſet their hand to the plough and now draws back;)</hi> look not out at the proſperity of the wicked (I ſay,) either within or without, nor at thy beſettings and huntings up and down, leaſt thy foot almoſt ſlide; but to God <hi>(that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livers out of all)</hi> let be thy eye of reſpect; and what then though thou ſee the Phariſee making his loud acclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; <hi>Lord, I thank thee, I am not thus and thus, nor a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this Publican, but pay tythe of all that I poſſeſſe, and faſt oft;</hi> (and the out-ſide of the Cup and Platter, made ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry clean) whereas thou art found daily ſmiting thy hand on thy breaſt, and art crying, <hi>Lord have mercy on me,</hi> &amp;c. and though his cry be ſtand off, I am holyer than thou; ſo that as <hi>Joſhua [the High Prieſt]</hi> hath been found ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding before the Lord <hi>(in his filthy vile raiment,)</hi> the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil hath been ready to reſiſt him, untill a voyce came from the Angel, take away his vile garment, and give him change of raiment, and thou in like manner ſeeſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in <hi>(in thy ſelf)</hi> but vileneſs, that (is) in thy fleſh, and if thou haſt ought to boaſt and rejoyce in <hi>(as of thy
<pb facs="tcp:44017:3"/>
ſelf;)</hi> it muſt be in that <hi>(only)</hi> and thy glorying <hi>(in thy infirmities;)</hi> which rather humbles thee, and is a Thorn in the fleſh, Satan to buffer, leaſt thou ſhould be exalted above meaſure <hi>(through the abundance of the Revelations of the Spirit,)</hi> that makes thee cry out, <hi>O wretched man that I am! who ſhall deliver me? and who ſhall change this vile body?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſay, Is this thy ſtate? and are thy ſins and tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions brought alwayes before thee? that ſomething ſeems yet to be imputed and laid to thy charge, and not all blotted out, and carried into the Land of forgetfulneſs, eſpecially when thou look among men of upbraiding minds, and corruptly bent (that are gone from the Spirit of God, that is liberal and upbraideth no man <hi>with things by-paſt,</hi> as doth the world, in the worldly nature, and ſpirit of miſchief, in their <hi>tatlings, tale-bearings, whiſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, backbitings,</hi> and falſe accuſations, and reportings <hi>(of evil)</hi> in a mind delighted therein, and therewith;) yet let not this any way trouble thee, as that thou ſhouldeſt be led into deſpondancy and doubtings, concerning the love, and mercy, and pity, and forgiveneſs of God; for Gods way is not like unto mans, not his thoughts like unto his, that is thus gone out of the life of God, out of the life of forgiveneſs, and mercy, and pity, and now would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voure and deſtroy <hi>(at once;)</hi> but this is the voyce of his Spirit <hi>(in the hearts of ſuch,)</hi> let not wickedneſſe be ſo much as once more mentioned amongſt you; for theſe things are but the ſhame of thy youth, and the reproach of thy widdow hood, which no more ſhall be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, nor charged againſt thee <hi>(by God,)</hi> ſince thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn hath been <hi>(indeed and in truth,)</hi> to him, and he is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to thee, and will blot out thy iniquities <hi>(by-paſt)</hi> and thy ſins will remember no more; becauſe theſe things were done in a ſtate and time of ignorance (in which God hath winked at thy faults, or corrected thee lightly <hi>(with Rods)</hi> and they are tranſgreſſions againſt the firſt Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, which the one offering hath made the attonement
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:44017:4"/>
for, and a way of reconciliation for thee <hi>(therein)</hi> in the fleſh of his body, that put an end to the many offerings under the Law, and alſo blots out all the infirmities <hi>(both of thy actings and offerings)</hi> in that ſtate; unto whom thou coming, (as unto a ſtone <hi>(indeed)</hi> diſallowed of by all the maſter builders of the earth, he is precious <hi>(in thy lively faith)</hi> as the head of the Corner: that was once offered up for all <hi>(in the eternal ſpirit of the Fathers good pleaſure)</hi> and is offered up no more, in that he hath for ever perfected them that are ſanctified.</p>
            <p>For in that ſpirit thou art come and returned to (that thou ſeeſt ſin a burden to thee, in, and of which thou art weary and heavy laden) God will freely blot out, and do all for thee, that haſt an offering brought before thee that is everlaſting, and ſo is the Covenant <hi>(thereof)</hi> in the eternal ſpirit <hi>(of him that ſanctifieth)</hi> and not as was, and is the offerings and Covenants under the Law, that were confirmed by ſtrength of words, and declarations of a Teſtament <hi>(in which a better good was ſhadowed out,)</hi> and the promiſes therein, and thereof, confirmed by an Oath, and ſtrong Proteſtations; but this is finiſhed (to and for all that can believe <hi>(therein,)</hi> whoſe Maker is their Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, the Lord of Hoſts is his name; and the betroth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>(here)</hi> is in righteouſneſſe, and in faithfulneſſe, and in loving kindneſſe <hi>(for ever;)</hi> and all that thou haſt to do, is to believe perfectly and fully, and wholly <hi>(in him, and the goodneſſe of his ſalvation;)</hi> and he will do all <hi>(for thee, and in thee,)</hi> without thy workings, and actings, and ſtrivings, and buſlings <hi>(in a mind cumbred with the cares and ſorrow of a life below, wherein thy ſoul hath been pierced through with many darts, and it hath been, and proved the worldly ſorrow that works death;)</hi> yea, and by it all thou couldeſt not adde a cubit to thy ſtature, but by believing in him that hath wrought, and done the work, it is finiſhed <hi>(to thee)</hi> in thy faith; for the queſtionings and reaſonings <hi>(thereof)</hi> with all the doubtings, and fear, and diſtruſt of God, are but the enemies work (of darkneſſe and cloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:44017:4"/>
thoughts, that hath vailed the extent of Gods goodneſs, and love, and pity, and mercy <hi>[to the ſouls neceſſity;]</hi> that the largeneſſe thereof <hi>(in the unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and unalterable bounty of his liberallity)</hi> hath not been apprehended and ſeen into; and all this continues by reaſon of unbelief, which the Son of God is come to deſtroy, and to that end is he manifeſt; and he thou muſt believe in <hi>[that is already come,]</hi> to work all thy works <hi>(in thee and for thee,)</hi> er'e it can be the work of the eternal ſpirit <hi>[in God,]</hi> and all to continue and remain eternally <hi>[with thee,]</hi> that of thy joy and rejoycing, there be no end, and the comfort everlaſting <hi>[that abides with thee,]</hi> that art comforted in the eternal Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, and what it works <hi>(Without thy help, as a Creature in the old man and ſtate;)</hi> but in the new man, as new created after God; in which thou art a meet help unto thy Maker, and fellow-worker together <hi>[with him,]</hi> to bring forth his works into manifeſtation and appearance; and then thou canſt ſay <hi>[truly,]</hi> that to deſtroy the works of the Devil is Gods work, and the end for which he was made manifeſt <hi>[in thy mortal fleſh,]</hi> and becauſe of that part <hi>(mortality, in which he hath wrought, and works,)</hi> thou haſt felt the work of mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to be <hi>[alſo]</hi> the work of God, and ſo is ſanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and juſtification; for it is God that muſt kill and make alive, and to all the works of the enemy, muſt make thee dead, and then holy and juſt <hi>[after himſelf;]</hi> which thou art on him waiting <hi>[to do for thee,]</hi> knowing that of thy ſelf thou art able to do nothing; and when thou haſt done all that thou canſt <hi>(as of thy ſelf)</hi> art but an unprofitable ſervant; yet that little ſtrength thou haſt <hi>[in God,]</hi> thou art ready and willing to put forth; becauſe thy faith <hi>[in God,]</hi> works by the Love of God <hi>ſhed abroad in thy heart,</hi> and ſo thou canſt ſhew thy faith by its work, the work of love; that is the ground and foundation of it <hi>(in thy heart;)</hi> in that of thoſe three, Faith, Hope, and Charity, that is the greateſt, as being the bond of perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction:
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:44017:5"/>
And this is it thou art differenced <hi>(by,)</hi> from the worſt of men, even by the love of God, and his grace, and favour <hi>(therein,)</hi> and flowing forth there-from, that thereby thou haſt a Chriſtians mark, and by all men art known to be a Diſciple and Follower of Chriſt, becauſe of thy love, by which thou art tranſlated from death to life, or that thou canſt not ſee any thing hurtful <hi>(to thee,)</hi> in the firſt death, even of the body <hi>(in, and under the enemies power fallen.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But in that thou art further reaſoning; yes this I believe, that God hath blotted out all my former tranſgreſſions, (now I am come to lay hold on him <hi>(by faith)</hi> and my ſins <hi>(in the time of ignorance)</hi> I believe are winked at, <hi>(by God,)</hi> but ſince that day I have ſinned, and come ſhort of the glory of God <hi>(who never did evil,)</hi> and this appears <hi>(to me)</hi> to be a ſin of wilfulneſſe, and a falling away after I have taſted of the Heavenly gift, and of the power of the world to come; and ſo being againſt the grace and favour of God (though I cannot ſay it was, and is in deſpite to the ſpirit of grace, but is through the weakneſs of the fleſh, that wars and luſteth againſt the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit <hi>(that is willing to obey and follow God (in the regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,) where-ever he goeth,</hi> yet there remains nothing but a fearful looking for of judgement, and fiery indignation from Heaven (on that part and nature <hi>in me,</hi>) that thus hath betrayed the Juſt under ſufferance <hi>(again)</hi> and hath crucified the Son of God afreſh; who in that he dyed once for all, dyeth no more <hi>(for me,)</hi> in that death hath no more dominion over him <hi>(but by and through me,)</hi> and there remains no more offering for ſin; therefore what have I to offer up to make a ſecond attonement?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The attonement is already made for thee (<hi>in</hi> thy <hi>faith,</hi>) though not in the doubting and unbelieving mind and part, for that was it that betrayed the Juſt under ſufferance <hi>(again,)</hi> and is the unrepenting part and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (of <hi>Eſau,</hi>) that hath been hunting abroad for its prey, and ſo hath loſt the bleſſing and birth-right, and cannot
<pb facs="tcp:44017:5"/>
again be renewed by any worldly ſorrow <hi>(in the dayly and hourly repentings of the worldly mind, that may ſeek a place of acceptance (thereof,) which cannot be found;)</hi> but in the Godly ſorrow is the repentance never to be repented of; and ſo Judgement witneſſed and born (again) on that mind, and part, and nature, that hath went out to the burdening and crucifying of the Juſt <hi>(afreſh;)</hi> and thus is <hi>Sion</hi> redeemed, even through the Spirit of judgement, and of burning, where the houſe of <hi>Eſau</hi> is as ſtubble, and the houſe of <hi>Joſeph</hi> for a flame, that leaves it neither root nor branch; and ſo the root of the matter <hi>(that was once within,)</hi> a bitter root of envy, and that hath luſted to vanity, and in which thou haſt uſed the liberty <hi>(of what had the beginning of its work in thee,)</hi> as an occaſion to the fleſh, and cloak of maliciouſneſſe; (that thy joy and content hath not continued, and the ſatisfaction thou once began to take <hi>(in God,)</hi> when thy Caſtle ſeemed to be ſtrong, and thou to ſay in thy heart, I ſhall never be moved, is not laſting, but in the hiding of Gods face to thee <hi>(in that ſtate,)</hi> thou art preſently troubled, this being removed by the Ax that is laid to the root of the tree <hi>(as thoſe hidden things of Eſau are ſought out)</hi> the matter is clearly ſeen, that hath cauſed the wound of the Daughter of Gods people to be healed deceitfully; and while the Core of corruption wrought <hi>(thus hiddenly and ſecretly)</hi> needs muſt there be the breakings out of the botches and boils, of that impoſterous infection of depraved nature, that hath contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted guilt on the ſoul, and made thee like a Tree that cumbers the good ground of God <hi>(in which his mercy, and pity, and grace, and forbearance hath wrought, for any honeſty of heart God hath beheld,)</hi> that being wearied out, and weary to bear thee <hi>[any long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,]</hi> the Angel Mowers are ſeen come forth to reap the earth; and a voyce comes, Cut it down, ſo: it hath a curſe, becauſe of unfruitfulneſſe <hi>[to him that looked for fruit, but beheld none,]</hi> no <hi>Figs</hi> for his taſte; and then why cumbers it the ground?</p>
            <p>So that that part in which the enemy hath wrought, after the grace, and love, and favour of God, is or hath been manifeſt <hi>(to a condition thy ſouls peace, and good is concerned in,)</hi> is that which the Judgement is to, that is to be laid to the Line, and Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to the Plummet, and ſo comes <hi>Sion [again]</hi> the Daughter of God, to be healed and cured perfectly, that is redeemed by
<pb facs="tcp:44017:6"/>
Judgement, and her Converts with Righteouſneſſe; and though the ſinner in <hi>Sion</hi> be afraid, and fear doth ſurprize the heart of the hypocrite <hi>[whoſe hope is periſhed and periſhing,)</hi> yet is not this <hi>[thee]</hi> that art again returned unto God, and doſt love his Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and canſt truly ſay, <hi>O how I love thy Law! that is ſweeter to me than the honey, and the honey-comb;</hi> and thy Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are not grievous, and burdenſome <hi>[to me;]</hi> no; though thou haſt felt a part, was afraid of Judgement, to which, and in which the fear of death wrought, and wherein was received the ſpirit of bondage, that it was made ſubject <hi>[to,]</hi> that feared death <hi>(on a part and mind, it delights [in] in the world;)</hi> where was the fearful looking for of judgement, and a ſpirit of bondage <hi>[received]</hi> again to fear, that concerning the coming of Chriſt <hi>[to judgement,]</hi> and his day of vengeance <hi>[on the world,]</hi> might be terrified with Letters and Epiſtles, becauſe of the falling away; for elſe that day had not come, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>And yet let this comfort thee, though many may be upbraiding thee, and thou mayeſt be made ſad, that God hath not made ſad; yea, though many may ſay, I am not ſo, and it hath not been ſo with me; but they have left thee ſmiting thy hand on thy breaſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> thou art rather juſtified <hi>[in this ſtate]</hi> than the other <hi>(he that thinks his ſtanding is, and hath been ſo ſure;</hi> (that is like a Rock) <hi>concerning whom it may be ſaid, his confidence is ſtrong, and on that Rock God will build his Church;)</hi> but being held in the wrong mind and part, and the confidence of, and in the fleſh, and ſelfs work (for ſee preſently, when the ſufferings are foretold of <hi>[to and in that part,] Maſter ſave thy ſelf,</hi> and then, <hi>Get thee behind me Satan;)</hi> Oh was not this the part to which the Corn, and Wine, and Oyl encreaſed! and that would ſay, <hi>It is good to be here,</hi> and would erect and build a Tabernacle in the transfiguring glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his raiment <hi>[ſhining,]</hi> and to hear a voyce from the glorious Majeſty, this was ſtrength and confidence enough <hi>(what never be moved?)</hi> but it was but the Lyons day yet, and he was not brought to lye down with the Lamb; but <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> was ſeen to be talking with the Lord <hi>of that glory,</hi> that by the roaring of the Lyon, made the Beaſts of the field to tremble; but ſee, the thing being come to be effected, <hi>that was foreſeen &amp; talked of,</hi> the Cock did but crow, and the Lyon trembles; this was ſelf-denyal
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:44017:6"/>
               <hi>indeed;</hi> for the way was making and preparing for the Lambs day, and all the ſelf-confidence proved but a Chriſt deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, that he might ſee himſelf, that by the Cock-crow had that fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told of, <hi>brought to remembrance,</hi> and then he went forth and wept bitterly; and after repentance aright, came to converſion <hi>(Peter, when thou art converted, ſtrengthen thy Brethren; but this might ſeem a ſtrange ſaying, after he had been his Follower and Diſciple;)</hi> and then could he tell of the more ſure word of propheſie, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto they did well to take heed, as unto a Light that ſhined in a dark place, untill the day dawned, and the day-ſtar to ariſe in the heart; here the Cock had crew, and the day had dawned, the Lambs day, and the day-ſtar had ariſen in <hi>the heart,</hi> and ſo no need of counſel from the wiſe men of the world <hi>concerning his birth;</hi> for he is come to feed his Lambs, his Sheep, and ſuch a Shepherd ſees his ſtar; for God who commanded the light to ſhine out of darkneſſe, hath ſhined in the dark heart, to give the knowledge of God in the face of Jeſus.</p>
            <p>Thus ſpake I comfortably <hi>to thee</hi> that haſt a ſence of theſe things; for while Gods face was hid, thou wert troubled; but now his countenance is lifted up, thou art more glad than when Corn, and Wine, and Oyl encreaſed <hi>[mark thee, more glad;]</hi> for there was gladneſſe then, and a face of the love of God, his countenance ſeemed to ſhine, and his favour to be on the dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling place; but this was but the aray of <hi>Solom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n in his glory,</hi> and the life was yet ſubdued in hope <hi>(that gloryed in an endleſſe joy and rejoycing;)</hi> yet was ſhut up under the Law, untill a faith af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward to be revealed; and then all the care is caſt on God, and the more ſure word heeded <hi>[that is that faiths begetter,]</hi> that leads out of the world, and to conſider the Lillyes glory, and for rayment and food is no care <hi>[in the worlds mind and ſpirit,]</hi> and <hi>Solomon</hi> in all his glory was not thus arrayed; where the life comes to be ſeen, more than meat, and the body, than raiment; and then ſeeſt thou all the things after which the Gentiles ſeek; and here is the faith of the elect of God, of Chriſt the Son of God: and the life I now live is by the faith of the Son of God <hi>(thou mayeſt truly ſay,)</hi> yet not thee, but Chriſt that lives in thee; and becauſe he lives, thou liveſt alſo; and he being revealed <hi>[in thee,]</hi> thou canſt ſay, <hi>Chriſt in me, the hope of glory;</hi> and ſo there
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:44017:7"/>
is no glorying in the fleſh, and any fleſhly appearance, but in him in whom is hid all the treaſures of wiſdome and knowledge; and then the fear <hi>in, and of the worldly mind, and all therein held and retained,</hi> comes to dye to thee, and in thee, and thee to, and in it, <hi>(as thou art found dead to the Law, which when it came, revived ſin, and thou dyed; for by it thou wert ſlain,)</hi> and then death hath no more dominion, but the Babe of ſalvation is lift up, and thou canſt ſay, <hi>Now let thy ſervant depart in peace, for mine eyes have ſeen thy ſalvation,</hi> &amp;c. And here the child dyes a hundred years old, and the ſinner a hundred years old, dyes accurſed; for the old man, that hath been waiting for the ſalvation of God, ſees the end of its expectation, and the ſervant <hi>[in the Houſe of God]</hi> that hath been faithful in all his Houſe, as <hi>Moſes</hi> was faithful therein <hi>[as a ſervant,]</hi> delivers up all to the Son, as the Builder of the Houſe <hi>(that is more worthy of honour than Moſes;)</hi> and ſo the old man and his deeds <hi>(that was, and is the tranſgreſſor, and is accurſed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law of its works,)</hi> comes to be judged and condemned <hi>[by Moſes in whom he hath ſeemed to truſt,]</hi> becauſe he was got into <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Seat, and Choice, and thou comeſt to dye, and be dead to him, and he to thee, and the dayly dying is known and witneſſed, and the dayly living <hi>[to God]</hi> felt; and the coſt and charge of the building is conſidered of, and counted; and all recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned on to be given up, and the life loſt for its ſouls ſalvation ſake; and what is here to loſe or be affraid of? ſeeing thou art reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to truſt God with all, both ſoul, body, and ſpirit, and the work of thy ſouls ſalvation; which thou canſt not any longer rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and diſpute, or queſtion and diſtruſt; but believe in the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and goodneſſe, and love, and mercy, and pity, and free-grace <hi>(of God)</hi> thou doſt; and if thou periſh, thou concludeſt it ſhall be in the hands of God (having nothing elſe to truſt in, nor no where elſe to fly; <hi>but as one which is ſtript of all earthly, and creaturely dependance,</hi> art reſolved there to lye and remain, even at the foot of mercy; and in it to reſt, and truſt, and confide, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till help and deliverance come, and ſpring up, and ariſe over all, beneath that which is eternal.</p>
            <p>And then thou ſeeſt, what-ever work is <hi>in thee, and for thee wrought,</hi> is by the Spirit of God, through thy faith therein, and not thine own work; but is Gods own work, <hi>in and by the Spirit
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:44017:7"/>
of his Son;</hi> that only doth praiſe God, and ſo doth not at all praiſe and glorifie ſelf, and boaſt in the fleſh, as that thou art this and this, and he is that; alaſs! no, of this thou art aſhamed, and to meddle of, and with controverſies <hi>about different opinions and judgements,</hi> or anoy and upbraid ſuch with any ſin and wickedneſs, <hi>that thou mayeſt get the victory and maſtery,</hi> is not thy work <hi>(in that Spirit of God thou art returned unto;)</hi> but readily ſayeſt, <hi>How can we boaſt in thoſe things, whereof we are now aſhamed?</hi> and God that knows my ſecrets, knows how it hath been with me, and what I have been; ſo that I find no cauſe to inſult and boaſt over any, nor to upbraid the worſt of men; for that doth but provoke unto miſchief, and ſtir up ſtrife and contention; and at beſt can but bring the creature to look at himſelf, and what he hath been and done, that may cauſe a looking back again <hi>(if the forgiveneſſe of God be not ſeen into;)</hi> and thus to bring off the mind from looking at God and his work <hi>[again,]</hi> that in love, and pity, and mercy, and ſalvation <hi>[to the ſoul of the creature,]</hi> had let him ſee himſelf, and a way to eſcape the ſnares, and baits, and temptation of Satan <hi>(through a ſence of forgiveneſs that came up in the manifeſting cauſe)</hi> to look at mens hardneſſe, and ruggedneſſe, and want of love and mercy, and pity, and forgiveneſſe, is not at all my work, but is beneath me, and out of my way <hi>[I walk in;]</hi> for it is not as I would be done by; in that God who hath healed my backſliding freely <hi>[for his own name ſake,]</hi> hath made me of the ſame mind to others; knowing that he is bleſſed that covereth and hideth ſin and tranſgreſſion, by converting a ſinner to God <hi>(where a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of fauls are blotted out;)</hi> and for me to uncover what God hath hid, and reveal, and di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cloſe anothers ſhame, and nakedneſs, would get me but an ill name, <hi>(that cannot delight in the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of any, as God doth not;)</hi> neither have I any joy to hear and ſee any ones backſlidings, but muſt pity them with my heart, and pray for, and wiſh their returne <hi>[again,]</hi> unto God, elſe I ſhould degenerate from what God hath made me, and change from my natural diſpoſition: And this is</p>
            <p>Becauſe God hath proved the good Phyſitian, and doth heal perfectly; he is the good <hi>Samaritan</hi> that binds up the wound; and in the day that I was caſt out in the open fields, when no eye pityed me, but I was naked, as in the day that I was born, neither
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:44017:8"/>
ſalted nor ſwadled at all, neither was I waſhed in water to ſupple me, nor any garment put on, and over me, to cover and hide my deformity; but I was in my blood, then did God pity me, and in my blood, ſaid, <hi>Live;</hi> and hath done all theſe things for me, though the Prieſt and Levite paſſed by, and there was no bowels among men [of that ſpirit,] and he being come to the loſt ſheep of the Houſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and to gather a remnant of the out-caſts of ſuch; and to call the ſinner to repentance, and not the righteous; and to the ſick, and poor, and needy, and weary, and maimed, having lift up his voyce, and ſtretched out his hand; what ſhall I turn my back againſt ſuch a work? ſhall I be offended becauſe he talks with the <hi>Samaritan</hi> woman <hi>(becauſe ſhe hath no fellowſhip with the Jewes?)</hi> and that becauſe he asketh her for water? or that he hath entred the houſe of a Phariſee, and there hath been found eating with the Publicans? Oh! no; ſuch work is not the work of God <hi>[in me,]</hi> but Gods work hath confounded it <hi>all of this nature;</hi> and the upbraider cannot ſtand here; in that I am come to the liberality of God, to the inlargedneſſe of heart <hi>to him,</hi> and to be upheld and ſuſtained, and ſupported <hi>by his free ſpirit;</hi> by the work of the Spirit of Truth, that makes free indeed; and to uſe my liberty as an occaſion to the fleſh, or cloak of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciouſneſſe, I cannot, nor dare, I be ſo imbondaged to <hi>Jew</hi> or <hi>Greek, Barbarian,</hi> or <hi>Scythian,</hi> bond or free, male or female, <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritan,</hi> or <hi>Phariſee,</hi> that I ſhould forget that love that would do good to all, and thinks well of the work of God towards all.</p>
            <p>So that concerning the Apoſtate, and Back-ſlider, and Prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal; I dare not accuſe any particular ſect, or opinion, or perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, or perſon of men <hi>(in ſuch perſwaſions,)</hi> as that you or thou art the only Apoſtate, and Backſlider; but I doe ſee a part <hi>(in all,)</hi> as it hath been and is wrongly perſwaded and opinionated, that until the creature be again returned <hi>(in it, and from the cauſe of its digreſſion, degeneration, and depravation,)</hi> is that Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, Back-ſlider, from the Commandements of God, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digal from the Spirit of truth, <hi>the Fathers houſe and dwelling place;</hi> to wit, the fleſh; and it was and is the cauſe of the breach between God and his creature, which no upbraidings can heal, neither is the Spirit of God <hi>(even it and him that God was in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the world began, reconciling it to himſelf;)</hi> but that all might
<pb facs="tcp:44017:8"/>
be laid waſt of this nature, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>(in and over all)</hi> theſe things hath b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> ſuffered, even breach up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on breach, and devotion upon devotion, and in the midſt of heapes of confuſion, is God come to and bringing up order; who muſt be, and himſelf (is) come to be, the healer, and repairer, and reſtorer thereof, ere the healing can be perfect; and by his Spirit <hi>that many are come to,</hi> they ſee into the cauſe and ground of all theſe things, and of all botches, and boyles, and putrified ſores, and breakings out <hi>(in the particulars of perſons, or in any particular people, gathered into a body (infected with the deadly wound of an impoſterous nature) under mens daubings with untempered morter, that cry peace while their mouths are put into;)</hi> and ſuch patched up health, could never long continue in a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealths body; but ſince God is come to do the work, and hath undertaken the cure, that will be the teacher of his people himſelf, their Councellour, Judge, Law-giver, Inſtructor, Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recter, Phyſitian, and All in all, I queſtion not a perfect cure of all that is amiſs, that ſuch are witneſſes of, that come unto him through faith, <hi>in the life of forgivneſſe, the Sons life,</hi> that is the repairer of all breaches, and the reſtorer again of a path to dwell in; and then out of all the ſelf-boaſtings and confidence <hi>in and of the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus, though ſin hath abounded, yet grace hath much more abounded; but not that we ſhould continue in ſin, God forbid; but all having ſinned and come ſhort of the glory of God, thou that art brought into the ſence hereof, art not in the worſt ſtate, neither is there any ground of deſpondency and doubtings <hi>(to thee)</hi> of Gods favour <hi>(of thee)</hi> thus returned into a ſence of the work of God, and into faith in the workers will and good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; whatever hard judgment and uſage thou meet with among men of different judgments and opinions; for thou art not left alone, and let them upbraid and mock on, be thou ſtill and wait in patience, out of the grumbling, murmuring, complaining nature, and thou wilt come over it all, and grow through all reproach <hi>of this nature,</hi> untill thou come to leave ſuch works withering and dying, as <hi>untimely fruit;</hi> but look thou at God <hi>in the midſt of all,</hi> and let them taunt on; they cannot hurt and ſtop thy glorying in <hi>a life that is out of the worlds reach to hurt,</hi> though in this life <hi>(of
<pb facs="tcp:44017:9"/>
the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſh, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>yings,)</hi> they may think they hurt thee; but thou art as willing to dye from that, as all things elſe, and thy repute is not a creaturely eſteem, but through bad reports haſt learned to paſſe, as well as good reports; and canſt ſay, <hi>If my hope was in this life, I was of all men moſt miſerable;</hi> but Chriſt <hi>in me</hi> is the hope of my glory, with whom my life is hid, and in him is hid all my treaſure, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And when he <hi>my life</hi> appears, I ſhall appear with him in glory. And that which hath been done in ſecret ſhall be manifeſt openly, and what ſpoken in the ear, preached on the houſe top; but until he appear <hi>to be my life,</hi> I muſt ſuffer with him, waiting for a further manifeſtation of his glory, and the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of the Son of God <hi>therein.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo for reports, alaſs! thou canſt not but know more of thy ſelf <hi>(in the root and ground of things, and that to the light and heart-ſearching ſpirit art come,)</hi> than men can have to accuſe thee; and now being come to know nothing by thy ſelf, yet thou art not thereby juſtified; what therefore is in this, more than to mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt the frame and temper of ſuch ſpirits? that yet have a root of the ſame hidden <hi>(that in thee hath broken forth,)</hi> and thou art therefore like to come firſt to the day of healing; for their co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering, and falſe healing, is the ſame that was thine; and thus have they been daubing, and are daubed <hi>(with untempered morter,)</hi> as thou wert; in that the ſame that hath been upbraiding <hi>(when it is diſpleaſed)</hi> will flatter when it is pleaſed, and is it that is flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered; deceiving; and being deceived: Therefore whatever they threaten, and wait to ſee <hi>concerning</hi> thee, wiſh not the ſame to them, <hi>(no not in thy heart, becauſe of him that ſeeth its ſecrets,)</hi> but wait on the Lord for preſervation, and the end of that ſpirits wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k thou ſhalt ſee <hi>manifeſt before thee,</hi> and ſhalt be made able to judge of it: And then, as to thy ſtate, thou wilt ſee, there is no need of a ſecond offering or attonement, for the offering is through the eternal Spirit, <hi>once for all,</hi> and the atonement for ever perfecting, <hi>in the ſanctified life,</hi> and in thy going from that Spirit, and the ſence therein and thereof begotten, the life of God hath been brought into a ſuffering ſtate, and to be afreſh cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, which thou being again returned to, and with the Spirit <hi>(that manifeſteth the cauſe thereof)</hi> come into unity, feeleſt the atonement make<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and the atonement making to be for ever;
<pb facs="tcp:44017:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
&amp; then what the many offerings <hi>(under the Law of works, where was the blood of Bulls, &amp; Goats of a year old, &amp; ſprinklings of an Heifer,)</hi> could not do, in that they make nothing perfect, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s pertaining to the Conſcience, thou being come to that which manifeſteth the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that the Bull was a figure of, and alſo the Goat <hi>[at left hand;]</hi> that being offered up and ſlain on the Croſſe, all ſufferance to the Lamb, <hi>(that went before for a peace-offering, and is the atone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment maker,)</hi> ceaſeth, and ſo the offering is but one, and once for all; that being offered to God, which his Spirit hath begotten and wrought; and the kindling and inflaming being of that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and ſo no falſe fire put into thy Senſure.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 2. All this I confeſſe very true to my condition, <hi>(con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the cauſe and ground of the apoſtaſie and back-ſliding, and falling away [from the truth of God] in the prodigality of that mind (a part and nature in the creature,) that could not be content to trust the Father withall, and to have the portion in his hands;)</hi> and now I plainly ſee that the Apoſtate and Backſlider, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digal, is not ſo much ſuch a Sect, or Opinion, and Perſwaſion, and People of ſuch a different Judgement from me <hi>(though I confeſſe in theſe different Perſwaſions, ſome are more deeply tainted with this apoſtatizing ſpirit, than other-ſome;)</hi> as the ſpirit and nature of a part <hi>(in all,)</hi> that hath backſliden from the Law and Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, and in the adulteration <hi>of that mind</hi> hath been cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the breach that is yet ſtanding, between God and his Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, untill the ſpirit of atonement and reconciliation, be ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and adhered to, that it make up all again: And ſeeing thou art not in <hi>Pauls</hi> ſtate <hi>(of unconverſion, from the ignorance of a blind zeal, that perſecuted, and ſpoke evil of that he knew not,)</hi> when concerning the Law, he could ſay, he was <hi>blameleſſe,</hi> yet was one at whoſe feet was laid the garments of the witneſſes; neither art crying, <hi>Lo here,</hi> or <hi>Lo there;</hi> or, <hi>I am of Paul, or Apollo,</hi> &amp;c. but art found comforting the Babe, and partaking with the afflicted in <hi>(their way,)</hi> and as one that hath paſſed through the ſtate and condition I am in, and that would not have ſin and wickedneſs countenanced <hi>(under any pretence whatever,)</hi> but the creature of God pityed in every ſtate <hi>(betrayed under the enemies power,)</hi> and yet the Axe of God layed to the root of the tree, and the root of the matter <hi>(relating to the cauſe and ground of the apoſtaſie and
<pb facs="tcp:44017:10"/>
backſliding from the truth of God,)</hi> ſeen into, that it may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved and taken out of the way of God <hi>utterly;</hi> the conditions of many being concerned herein, I further query, how and when it came in? and how it may be removed again <hi>(perfectly?)</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is generally the voyce and cry of the world, it came in but juſt now, and that the deceiver entred but as in their dayes <hi>(and yet excuſe themſelves of his entring of them, that they may lay the burden heavy on others.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The firſt Apoſtate was old <hi>Adam,</hi> that went from the guidance and government of the Spirit of God; and as all have taken a nature and part from him <hi>(who was of the earth earthly, and as was the earthly, ſo are they that are earthly,)</hi> though he was made a living ſoul, <hi>nevertheleſs,</hi> the ſoul that ſinned having dyed <hi>(in the day he eat of the forbidden fruit,)</hi> and ſo death having paſt over all from <hi>Adam,</hi> &amp;c. all are to wait <hi>(again)</hi> for, and in the power of the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> a quickning ſpirit; and yet as to the firſt man <hi>(as he was, and is a natural man,)</hi> he was betrayed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and into this ſtate, and is not properly reckoned for the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and offender and tranſgreſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r <hi>(as to the natural part;)</hi> further than creatures <hi>(in it,)</hi> are ſo joyned and united to the cauſe <hi>(there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,)</hi> that they neglect the work of that, and him, who gives the ſight of the miſery <hi>(of ſuch ſtate,)</hi> and ſo in the end comes to ſleight and diſ-regard the remedy out of it; for the miſtery of iniquity <hi>(that hath wrought, and yet works in the hearts of many opp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſers of the work of the Spirit of Truth there,)</hi> is ſpiritual wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in high places; ſo that though death came on the bodyes of all, as by one man that ſinned <hi>(they have taken a nature and part from,)</hi> for the ſouls ſake, that is immortal, whom the tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and anguiſh hath reſted on; as a death that came by reaſon and means of ſin; yet the feeling of a remedy to the one <hi>(to wit, the ſoul, once relapſed and fallen under the power of a ſecond death,)</hi> is through the begettings and working up of a faith in the ſpirit of him that endured the one, for the conquering the dominion and power of both.</p>
            <p>Thus is there a man of ſin, or man by whom came ſin, whom God will deſtroy by the breath of his lips and noſtrils, and bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his appearance <hi>(with an everlaſting deſtruction,)</hi> and yet not properly the firſt man <hi>Adam,</hi> and natural body <hi>(of elements,)</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:44017:10"/>
the creature of God was betrayed <hi>(in)</hi> under the enemies power; but he in all the world is to be redeemed and reſtored <hi>(to wit the creature of God,)</hi> and nothing loſt <hi>[of him,]</hi> that comes into his hands, <hi>who is the Redeemer and Reſtorer:</hi> yet as the Elements are not properly the creature of God, but that which the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture embodyed a being [in,] to and for ſelf; for redemption ſake <hi>(from a ſtate it was fallen in under, and of the body that ſuffered, and which he ſuffered [in,] through the fall;)</hi> as ſelf comes thus to be deſtroyed <hi>[by a deſtruction that is everlaſting,]</hi> the body thereby coming to ſuffer under the power of a death and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction <hi>[in time and place,]</hi> is reſtoring in time and place, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored out of time and place <hi>(in the end thereof, that was the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning;)</hi> and then the firſt beauty is known, which God created all things beautiful in, <hi>(when he ſet the world in their hearts, that no man can find out the works of God, from the beginning to the end;)</hi> which is all the work of the Spirit of God, and attained by a faith therein, where is <hi>[only]</hi> everlaſting ſafety, in a feeling of the ſpirit of the world, and the way and courſe thereof <hi>(it hath led into, and under,)</hi> that hath made the body vile <hi>(in the oldneſſe of that ſtate, ſelf hath made miſerable and wretched,)</hi> and then are the groanings and ſighings felt, of that and him that hath begotten into a ſence of the Spirits ſufferance <hi>(that makes interceſſion with that which cannot be uttered,)</hi> and ſo a fellow-feeling of the ſufferers glory dwelt in <hi>(in a hope that keeps waiting [for,] and faith that believes [in,] the perfect, and thorow redemption and reſtoration [again,] of the creature (into a ſtate it is fallen from.)</hi> Therefore</p>
            <p>The firſt Apoſtate being deſcribed <hi>[in his place,]</hi> with the ground and cauſe thereof <hi>[to wit of the apoſtaſie,]</hi> this I have fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſay to the remaining root <hi>(of what continues undeſtroyed of the part and nature that was, and is found in the cauſe;)</hi> Though the cauſe of the firſt breach was found in the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> (in a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture he became embodyed [in] male and female:) where the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man was moſt properly ſeen and found in the cauſe of the firſt tranſgreſſion againſt, and erring and ſtraying from the Spirit of God; yet that being not ſo much the cauſe and ground of the apoſtaſie, as the deceitful healing <hi>[is,]</hi> after the breach hath been made; wherein <hi>Adam</hi> hath been found hunting about the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and running among the Trees <hi>[for ſhelter,]</hi> as one afraid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:44017:11"/>
of tranſgreſſion, and making to them aprons and coverings of Fig-leaves; let this be throughly ſearched into; and then all falſe coverings muſt off, and the root will come to be removed <hi>(from whence the cauſe of all complaints hath proceeded,)</hi> untill which time the daubings will be <hi>ſtill,</hi> but with untempered mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, and the falſe gloſſe will remain over every work of fallen man; and here you will find the cauſe to be the nature of what was firſt degenerated <hi>[from God,]</hi> and ſtill is generated <hi>[in,]</hi> the cauſe and ground of the mans fall and backſliding; in which came up a Law, which ſin and the man of ſin took occaſion [by,] and offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings under the Law, which made nothing perfect, as pertaining to the Conſcience; but ſerved for the bringing in of a better hope, a hope in a better life (then that of the fall and tranſgreſſion from God, which all creatures live, and move, and have their being <hi>(in)</hi> under the ſufferance of Gods Spirit, as that which came and was taken from him, but abode not in his will and good pleaſure;) ſo that as far forth as any mans hope of glory is in this life, the Law is not at an end, nor the one offering reſted and truſted (in,) that makes a perfect-atonement, but the remembrance is tinctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the firſt Prieſt-hoods work <hi>(whoſe lips was to preſerve knowledge,)</hi> and ſo ſin again is brought to the remembrance, after there hath been a coming to the one offering, that was offered up once for all; and the Law can never be put an end to <hi>(here,)</hi> the bringing up of which declared the everlaſting High Prieſt to be come, and an everlaſting Prieſthood, the atonement maker for all; but ſince the Watch-men hath been hunted after, and there hath been a going down into <hi>Egypt</hi> for help <hi>(as if there was no Balm in Gilead, or no Phyſitian there,)</hi> it is ſeen what they have done, and what is the moſt that the many Paſtors can do? even ſmite, and wound, or take away thy vail; ſo that thou muſt get thee out beſides the Shepherds Tents, to find the place he makes his flock to lye down in, and reſt <hi>at noon-day,</hi> even in him that is a ſhadow from the heat, and refuge from the ſtorm; experience being my beſt Teacher, <hi>in this condition, I ſee no truſting in man, but vain is the hope of all ſuch confidence;</hi> and now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing returned to God, I find a place of ſafety, ſomething of bread in my own houſe, and water in my own Ciſtern; and it being my own, and not a ſtrangers; here I come to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:44017:11"/>
ſet down under my own vine, and under my own fig-tree, and none can riſe up to make me afraid; but God is to me all that I want or ſtand in need of, both Husband, Teacher, Phyſitian, and all in all, and what need can I have <hi>[here,]</hi> either of fruit of my body to rejoyce in? or ſubſtance of and for my ſouls content; of cure for my wounds, or health to my diſeaſe; ſince in him is both health to my ſoul, and counſel and advice [is] in him, to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer all my diſquietneſs: oh I have enough! ſince I have again found him whom my ſoul loves, this is my firſt beloved, whom I will hold, and never more will let him go; when he meets me without, he ſatisfieth me with kiſſes, and this is he I have longed for all my life long.</p>
            <p>And now I am over-joyed at his coming, at our meeting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, to finde his Armes ſo open, and feel his imbraces ſo neer; though I had put him off with delays, and had wandred after o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lovers, untill I ſaw my way hedged up with thornes, that I could no longer paſs on, and that I was among the ſwine, <hi>(in a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digality of the Harlots love,)</hi> and there longed for my belly full of husks, but there was found none to give them me; I had a yoak of oxen to try, and a wife to marry, and father to bury; and having put off my coat, ſaid, how ſhall I put it on? and having waſhed my feet, how ſhall I defile them? yet he never hath me denied <hi>(in what ever I have been found asking [in faith;])</hi> and this breaks my heart more than all, his love, notwithſtanding my ingratitude; but being thus returned, I find in the houſe, a home-born ſon, that is elder <hi>by birth,</hi> than I; and he hath the name of a Jew, but is only one outwardly, for inwardly he is ravening, though his begrutchings and grumblings <hi>[at me,]</hi> are alwayes with this exclamation, Thou knoweſt I never went out of the houſe, as hath this prodigall, and played ſuch pranks as he, but have abode alwayes at home, and now muſt the beſt robe be fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched down for him? and muſt there be the muſick for him, and the fatted calf killed? when didſt thou ever thus for me? Thus is the repiner <hi>(at the Fathers will and good pleaſure)</hi> a dayly bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to my ſoul; for it came into my heart to return to my father, and to ſay, <hi>Father I have ſinned againſt heaven, and againſt thee, and am no more worthy to be called thy ſon, make me as one of thy hired ſervants (conſidering that in my fathers houſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> was many ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:44017:12"/>
and they had bread enough, and I a ſon did want;)</hi> and find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his love and forgiveneſs beyond compare, as much was forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven me, ſo I cannot but love much, and therefore the father be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing found falling on my neck and kiſſing me, and crying out, <hi>This my ſon was loſt, and he is found, he was dead and he is alive;</hi> the whole earth is diſquieted at the matter; And he that was a Jew <hi>[outwardly]</hi> and was broken off, for the reconciling of the world, whoſe receiving in again ſhould be as life from the dead, hath been found nothing at all differing from the Gentile that had the outward Court given into his hands to trample on, and now hath been found exerciſing authority and Lordſhip over the flock and heritage of God, that would boaſt it ſelf againſt the branches, as though he bare the roote, and not the roote him; for the Lyon being come forth of the thickets, and the deſtroyer of the Gentile on his way, one is found that hath again perſwaded <hi>Japhet</hi> to dwell in the Tents of <hi>Shem,</hi> though once it was ſayd, <hi>Who ſhall?</hi> And this hath broken down the wall, and here is neither Jew nor Greek, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but the Lyon lyes down with the Lamb, and gives up the day to him, as he hath had his day; ſo that while the wrath is kindled but a little, there is a truſting in him, and a kiſſing the Son, leaſt he be angry, <hi>and the Sun go down in wrath;</hi> and becauſe of this <hi>bleſſed,</hi> the whole earth is amazed, as ſuch that call to the rocks and mountains to fall on them, and hide and cover them from the wrath of the Lamb; in that flying from a Lyon <hi>that was in their way,</hi> a Bare hath met them, and laying their hands, and leaning on a wall, a Cockatrice hath bitten them; and that which might have been killed and trampled on <hi>[in the Egg]</hi> is now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a fiery flying Serpent.</p>
            <p>And what now ſhall I ſing? but, oh the Lambs day! here is no need of Sun by day, nor Moon by night, but the Lamb is the light of the glorious City, which is as the light of ſeven dayes, and is Lord of Lords, and King of Kings, and the Government is on his ſhoulders, that hath brought on a mountain where none can hurt and deſtroy, ſo that greater is the glory of the latter houſe, then the glory of the firſt <hi>(in which the grumbler is found, as that which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> never went out of, but is the outward Court [only] the Gentile hath troden under foot;)</hi> And how doth my ſoul ſing, to ſee this day? in that greater is he that is in us, than he that is in the world,
<pb facs="tcp:44017:12"/>
that doth hate and perſecute us, and hath ſpoken all manner of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil againſt us, for the name-ſake of God, though once we were our own, and went whither we would; but now we are bought with a price, and another girds us, and carries us where we would not, and all the wayes of ſin and wickedneſs, we hate with a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect hatred, and count it worſe than poyſon to the body, <hi>(what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we have been)</hi> and fly from it more than from a Lyon; And this is my living teſtimony before a heart-ſearching God, that I would rather preſently and immediately dye and be ſtricken with the wound of a bitter enemy, than in my ſelf or any one elſe <hi>(wittingly and willingly)</hi> countenance any thing a known ſin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Spirit of God, it being my burden to look back on what I have offended him in.</p>
            <p>Therefore now will I ſing a ſong of my well beloved, of the ſalvation of my God, from his own work that doth praiſe him <hi>[in my heart,]</hi> who is to me my all, my King, that in a time of need <hi>[to me]</hi> deliverance did bring, that from all hurt my ſoul redeemed, and from the ſting, of death, of grave, of hell, of bitter pangs; when enemies without and within did hunt, to catch my feet in ſnares, and ſought to wound, the precious life of what in love rebounds to God in thanks, above all mortals reach; Oh he doth ſtill ſupport! that keeps me freſh, to live to love, and love to praiſe his name, that doth ſurround, while I abound, and ſtill its he, is my enough, that fills my cup, that ſweetens all, he is my Phyſitian, my ſtay, my ſtaff of bread, of water, my rock, my ſong, that empties, that fills, that makes poor, that makes rich, that kills, that makes alive, that is to me a Garden encloſed, a watered bank, a fountain ſealed, from the rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers reach; I am loſt, and again am found; in him, I mourn, and then I ſing, becauſe I am full, and yet cannot have too much of him; and this I ſeal with life, with blood, with croſs, that hath a Crown, becauſe my crown is loſt, it is caſt down; in that which frontils high, did never deny, could never withſtand; for it's in breaſt, and not in tongue, nor yet a hand, an empty hand, oh, no! it's that which can command, and yet I chuſe, that I may refuſe, what love would abuſe; and make that grow cold, which makes me ſo bold, in what doth with-hold; in boaſting above, the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of love, that purely doth move, to kiſs and imbrace, the lips
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:44017:13"/>
of that face, whoſe heart doth grace, the virgins eye, that can e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpy, who is ſo nigh; to bleſs a Troop, that now can ſtoop, to hear my voyce, that doth rejoyce, <hi>The Babe.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="postscript">
               <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
               <l>IF curious eyes, or ſubtill wits, would judge what here I write,</l>
               <l>They firſt muſt loſe, what I have done, and that will give them ſight</l>
               <l>Into the order I behold, that is not grac'd with art,</l>
               <l>But doth be fool, and then make wiſe, to learn another part;</l>
               <l>Then that which leaves a roade for fools, to taunt in verſe or rhime,</l>
               <l>As though to voyce they ſeet would make, that he may go betime;</l>
               <l>That coming forth ſo ſoon, is lamed, and then its hard to find,</l>
               <l>The minds right way, to be received, in what its made thus blind.</l>
               <l>Firſt croſt, then loſt, till up in view all's brought,</l>
               <l>That blinds the minde, that ſeeks to finde out ſuch a work is wrought,</l>
               <l>Which ſhews the cauſe, why peace is loſt, with God, and then with man,</l>
               <l>And while its loved, can't be removed, let wit do what it can;</l>
               <l>For who can ſay, that this I was, but I can yet ſay more,</l>
               <l>That once was courted for my wit, which each Sects did adore;</l>
               <l>Both high and low, both poor and rich, the ſmall and eke the great,</l>
               <l>In many caſes made me Judge, when I refuſ'd the ſeat;</l>
               <l>But I ſeek [now] a ſervants place, and yet am oft controul'd,</l>
               <l>Becauſe through love, I chuſe a life, that durſt not ſelf imbold;</l>
               <l>As ſure do thoſe, that once I thought, poſſeſt a better place,</l>
               <l>Than I can ſee them keep or hold, to make their name a grace;</l>
               <l>And therefore ſince, I this have loſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, what more have I to loſe,</l>
               <l>That once was clipt about, in armes, of ſuch that me did chuſe;</l>
               <l>Before the Nobles of the earth, that ſure were left behinde,</l>
               <l>To chuſe what I had choſen firſt, which they could never finde;</l>
               <l>Yea in the lap of favour was a knee, where I was dandled,</l>
               <l>How ever roughly I am uſ'd, and courſely I am handled;</l>
               <l>But now caſt down, I hath my Crown, and count it all but droſs,</l>
               <l>That once ſeem'd gold, for to behold; though dung, its made my croſs;</l>
               <l>Croſſed, crowned, renowned, and all in one, and in that one is all,</l>
               <l>That keeps me ſafe, on ground to walk, while climbers take a fall;</l>
               <l>Ah bleſſed God! be thou my guide, and keep me to thy praiſe,</l>
               <l>And thou ſhalt have both heart and minde, given up to thee alwayes.</l>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. B.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
